<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description>Thoughts on math, computing, and data</description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 01 Nov 2019 15:30:33 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A Painless Introduction to Python Data Analysis and Visualization</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Data visualization and data science is a hot topic right now, and there's lots of people I know who
want to develop this skill set. A common hurdle, in my experience, is that a lot of tutorials are
either incredibly specific (here's how to change the y-axis title) or very abstract (this is what a
violin plot is, good luck making one!) The goal of this tutorial is to make the kind of resource I
would have really benefited from when I was starting out: an introduction that can give you the
background you need to actually benefit from internal documentation and give you an idea of what's
possible so you aren't reinventing the wheel (an extraordinarily common problem). This post is
written for:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who aren't completely new to computer programming, but not necessarily programmers or software developers
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to know basic Python syntax to follow along, but you don't need to actually know much about Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who is tired of the limitations of programs like Tableau and wants to be able to make
bespoke visualizations that meet their specific needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those who are interested in using Python for statistics or machine learning who want some
wider background before they start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students or presenters of any kind who want to make beautiful graphs without fighting Excel for
an hour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If any of these describe you, you've come to the right place!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (42 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 19:07:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bayesian Fallacies, Part 2: The Math of the PSAT Math Section</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In the last episode, we introduced two thinking errors that often come up in statistics: Bayes'
paradox and regression to the mean. I proposed that these errors are really two different
manifestations of the same underlying phenomenon, but I haven't done much to actually explain
why. This post will lay the mathematical groundwork for that explanation!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (11 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:18:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bayesian Fallacies, Part 1: Of Test Scores, Ski Jumps, and Diseases</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In my intro psych class, we discussed two distinct &lt;i&gt;fallacies&lt;/i&gt;: common systematic errors in how humans
think. These are called &lt;i&gt;Bayes' Paradox&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;regression to the mean&lt;/i&gt;. I will claim that both of these
are really manifestations of the same underlying issue, and in actuality are mathematically the
same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is going to be pretty involved and pretty long, so I'll be splitting it up into parts. The
first part will just cover the basics of what these two fallacies are and provide a mathematical
framework. After that I'll be using computers to analyze the two, and then I'll make the math behind
what we're doing more rigorous.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (13 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 18:17:52 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Hello, World!</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/hello-world/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is the first public page for this blog: a place where I will record thoughts and essays on
various topics, usually pretty close to the intersection of math, data, and computing. There will be
some pretty heavy mathematical topics as well as much lighter fare: my hope is that people of varied
math and computer science backgrounds can find something useful for them.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
So, hello world!&lt;sup&gt;&lt;a id="fnr.1" class="footref" href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/hello-world/#fn.1"&gt;1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/sup&gt; I thought the first thing I should probably do is explain why I go by the tag
&lt;code&gt;PollardsRho&lt;/code&gt; in various places and why I decided to give this blog the title "Pollard's Rho." Simply
put, it's my favorite algorithm: kind of an esoteric category to have a favorite in, but I'm sure by
the end of this you'll see what I mean.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/hello-world/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>algorithms</category><category>cs</category><category>meta</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/hello-world/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 02 Aug 2019 23:35:07 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>