<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description>Thoughts on math, computing, and data</description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 01:40:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Effective Data Visualization, Part 1: What Is Effective Data Visualization?</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This series is the textual version of a presentation I gave to a class on
effective&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;data visualization. I'm reproducing it here both to add some
information that&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;was cut from the presentation for time and to put it in a
publicly available&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;place.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org286fd4f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org286fd4f"&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org286fd4f"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org8e64dca" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8e64dca"&gt;What This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8e64dca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This series of posts is about how to make effective data visualization: exactly
what I mean by that will become clear shortly. Much like one might critique
writing in a creative writing class, I'll focus on how to improve existing
visualizations. This should hopefully also help the reader become a better
consumer of data visualization they encounter in their daily lives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0a68252" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0a68252"&gt;Who This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0a68252"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This guide is for anyone! Unlike my other work on this blog, this guide expects
no knowledge of coding or any platform for visualizations: learning such a tool
is necessary to implement these ideas, but not necessary for this guide at all.
My hope is that this is generally useful for people in business, data science,
journalism, programming, and statistics: anyone who works with or cares about
data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Without further ado, let's get started!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:34:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Basics of Cryptography, Part 3: Cryptographic Hashes</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-3-cryptographic-hashes/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This is the third post in a series: for part 1, go &lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and for part 2, go &lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-2-intro-to-rsa/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
We've previously discussed cryptography, in the modern world, as a way of sending secure messages
through insecure channels. But this is not the only thing you might want to do in a world with
malicious actors trying to thwart you. RSA and Diffie-Hellman exchange aren't vulnerable to simple
eavesdroppers. However, there are other types of attacks that they don't protect against, and we
might want to insulate ourselves against those attacks as well. One of them is a &lt;i&gt;man-in-the-middle&lt;/i&gt;
attack—in essence, someone manipulating messages. As we've often done, let's imagine a scenario, the one
I ended the last post with:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
Alice and Bob are organizing anti-government activism in a country that represses political
freedoms. Alice wants to tell Bob to meet her in a certain place, but they can only communicate over
the Internet: Bob worries that Malcolm, the government employee that controls their Internet
provider, will forge a message from Alice and set him up. How can Bob verify that Alice's messages
haven't been modified?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-3-cryptographic-hashes/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-3-cryptographic-hashes/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 19:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Basics of Cryptography, Part 2: Intro To RSA</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-2-intro-to-rsa/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
This is part 2 of a series: to see the first post, go &lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/"&gt;here.&lt;/a&gt; If you're not familiar with things like
modular arithmetic, read that before reading this.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we're going to continue to look behind the curtain at the algorithms that power the Internet
we know and love. In this post, I'll cover the RSA cryptosystem: what it is, what it does, how it
works, etc. RSA is such a useful algorithm because it sidesteps a lot of the problems with sending
secure messages we talked about last time. You can think of it as a clever way of improving on the
encryption model we used last time, not by simply improving it as it exists, but by completely
sidestepping the security problems it had.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This post will introduce a pristine version of RSA, without the real-world complications, and apply
it to the same problem we looked at last time: securely sending a message to someone else over an
insecure channel, without prior communication. In the future, I'll look at how this textbook RSA
fails in the real world, and additionally how you can use the idea behind RSA to do things besides
sending secure messages.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-2-intro-to-rsa/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-2-intro-to-rsa/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 21 Jan 2020 20:14:55 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem Solving Techniques: Induction</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-induction/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This is the second in my series on problem-solving techniques: for the first, see &lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/"&gt;this post on invariants.&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
As I've previously discussed, I'm fascinated by the ability to create proofs or solutions for
problems that are easy to understand but difficult to synthesize. In this series, I'm trying to shed
some limited insight on how we mere mortals can arrive at these beautiful and creative insights.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-induction/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (13 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-induction/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2020 18:53:20 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Basics of Cryptography, Part 1: Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
How can we send secure messages through insecure channels?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A quick note before we begin: this summarizes a talk I gave at my high school's computer science
club. It's written to be accessible to anyone with a basic math background, though, and it doesn't
require any programming knowledge. This is the start of a series that will try to explain the basics
of cryptography: given that all of us use cryptography every day, it's important to have a basic
understanding of how it works. It's also pretty cool!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 16:09:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PACTF 2019 Writeup: How'd I Get Hacked?</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-howd-i-get-hacked/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
As I mentioned &lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-denial-of-service-attack/"&gt;in this post&lt;/a&gt;, I wrote several problems for PACTF 2019, a cybersecurity and
programming competition held for high schoolers. I've been asked to do writeups for each of the
problems I did, and so I'll be trying to do that—at least, where I think there's something
interesting to talk about for the people reading this who didn't compete and don't care about the
contest. 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today, we'll be going over "How'd I Get Hacked?", which gives me an opportunity to talk about one of
my favorite niche programming topics: the utter insanity and brilliance of Unicode.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-howd-i-get-hacked/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (8 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pactf</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-howd-i-get-hacked/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 13 Jan 2020 04:44:37 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem-Solving Techniques: Invariants</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of clever proofs in mathematics and computer science. I've already talked about some
of them, and I hope to do a lot more of it on this blog. There's often a certain separation that I
feel when I read something particularly creative or beautiful: this is amazing, but how could I ever
hope to produce something like it? Is real aesthetic achievement in these fields limited to those
with a natural talent I lack? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm still not sure about that last question, but I do know that, like anything, it is possible to
improve at creative problem-solving through practice. The people I've known who have been best at
doing creative math—the kind that makes perfect sense when you see it but seems impossible to find
if you don't already know it—have built up vast toolboxes of concepts and ideas that are useful in
many different ways across mathematics and computer science. These aren't solutions for a single
problem: they're meta-solutions that serve as an archetype for solutions to a diverse array of
problems. In my experience, the size of that toolbox is what, more than anything else, determines
how effectively one can find creative, novel ways of approaching problems. I'll be talking about one
such tool today: invariants.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:26:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>PACTF 2019 Writeup: Denial of Service Attack</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-denial-of-service-attack/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Last year, I led the team behind &lt;a href="https://2019.pactf.com/"&gt;PACTF 2019&lt;/a&gt;, a CTF competition where people, mostly high schoolers,
solved problems based on computers and computer security. It was a really fun and rewarding
experience, and I think a lot of people hopefullly had fun solving the problems. If that sounds like
something you might like, I'd recommend trying it out: make an account and see what you can do! I
wrote about a dozen problems for this contest, and so you'll see some overlapping themes with what I
talk about on this blog.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Someone recently asked me to write up my explanation for one of the problems I wrote: "Denial of
Service Attack", one of the harder problems in the second week.  You're welcome to try the problem
on the PACTF website in full before we begin. I will be spoiling the whole thing here: you've been
warned! I'll start with a brief overview, give some background, and go over the main trick.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-denial-of-service-attack/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (6 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pactf</category><category>programming</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/pactf-2019-writeup-denial-of-service-attack/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 06 Jan 2020 02:39:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Whirlwind Tour of Statistical Tests</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Hello again! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's say you've been working on your dataviz skills, and you think you've found an interesting
pattern or correlation in a dataset. How can you tell that whatever you're seeing is significant?
How can you distinguish between random variation and legitimate, meaningful results? As it happens,
the mathematical branch of statistics is almost entirely devoted to questions like these. I think
aspiring data scientists need not be full-fledged statisticians, but everyone should be familiar
with the basic statistical tests, when to apply them, and how to interpret their results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we'll be sojourning through the land of statistical tests in Python, showing how they might be
used and interpreted. The goal is not that you'll be able to apply this all immediately when you
need it; instead, the goal is that you can recognize when statistical tests might be useful and be
able to find the ones you need. (In an age of the Internet, I find recognition to be much more
important than memorizing everything: if you know what to Google, you can figure out how to code it,
but you can't Google something you can't put into words or something you can't recognize.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (20 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>guide</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 17:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Painless Introduction to Python Data Analysis and Visualization</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Data visualization and data science is a hot topic right now, and there's lots of people I know who
want to develop this skill set. A common hurdle, in my experience, is that a lot of tutorials are
either incredibly specific (here's how to change the y-axis title) or very abstract (this is what a
violin plot is, good luck making one!) The goal of this tutorial is to make the kind of resource I
would have really benefited from when I was starting out: an introduction that can give you the
background you need to actually benefit from internal documentation and give you an idea of what's
possible so you aren't reinventing the wheel (an extraordinarily common problem). This post is
written for:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who aren't completely new to computer programming, but not necessarily programmers or software developers
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to know basic Python syntax to follow along, but you don't need to actually know much about Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who is tired of the limitations of programs like Tableau and wants to be able to make
bespoke visualizations that meet their specific needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those who are interested in using Python for statistics or machine learning who want some
wider background before they start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students or presenters of any kind who want to make beautiful graphs without fighting Excel for
an hour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If any of these describe you, you've come to the right place!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (44 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 19:07:24 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>