<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho (Posts about dataviz)</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/categories/cat_dataviz.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 21:50:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Effective Data Visualization, Part 1: What Is Effective Data Visualization?</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This series is the textual version of a presentation I gave to a class on
effective&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;data visualization. I'm reproducing it here both to add some
information that&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;was cut from the presentation for time and to put it in a
publicly available&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;place.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-orgbefca19" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgbefca19"&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgbefca19"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org583984e" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org583984e"&gt;What This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org583984e"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This series of posts is about how to make effective data visualization: exactly
what I mean by that will become clear shortly. Much like one might critique
writing in a creative writing class, I'll focus on how to improve existing
visualizations. This should hopefully also help the reader become a better
consumer of data visualization they encounter in their daily lives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org7b6ac65" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org7b6ac65"&gt;Who This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org7b6ac65"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This guide is for anyone! Unlike my other work on this blog, this guide expects
no knowledge of coding or any platform for visualizations: learning such a tool
is necessary to implement these ideas, but not necessary for this guide at all.
My hope is that this is generally useful for people in business, data science,
journalism, programming, and statistics: anyone who works with or cares about
data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Without further ado, let's get started!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-orgac1be72" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="orgac1be72"&gt;What is Effective Data Visualization?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-orgac1be72"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
What do I mean by &lt;i&gt;effective&lt;/i&gt; data visualization? Here, an effective data
visualization is one that effectively helps the viewer process information. I
care here about dataviz as a tool that increases our brains' ability to work
with data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is contrasted with purely aesthetic concerns. Some visuals that don't look
spiffy are nonetheless useful tools, and some visuals that are aesthetically
unappealing are useful processing aids.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Data can be deadly serious, and so data visualization can have tremendous
importance.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/images/teachback/ChristaMcAuliffe.jpg" alt="nil"&gt;
The &lt;i&gt;Challenger&lt;/i&gt; disaster in which Christa McAuliffe, the person in the photo
above, died is a grim reminder of information's power. The O-ring failure
that led to the explosion was preventable and understood. Thus, some authors
like Edward Tufte have analyzed this tragedy as a failure of data visualization
as much as anything else: the visualizations used to communicate the dire need
to reschedule the launch failed to convey this knowledge to the people who made
that fateful decision. This is to say that effectively communicating and
understanding data is worthy of serious study.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Why use data visualization at all? Why not use other tools, like spreadsheets or
statistics?
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org91a1834" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org91a1834"&gt;Why is Effective Data Visualization?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org91a1834"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
There's a persistent myth that graphs are inherently less meaningful or useful
than raw statistics. Statistics are very important, and I would certainly not
advocate for replacing the statistics underlying, say, clinical trials with a
bunch of graphs.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The classic example of why we might use data visualization in addition to
statistics comes to use from Frank Anscombe in the form of 4 different datasets
like this one:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="1" class="dataframe"&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr style="text-align: right;"&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;x&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;y&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.04&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.95&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;13.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.58&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.81&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;11.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;8.33&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;14.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.96&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;6.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.24&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.26&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;12.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;10.84&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;4.82&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;5.68&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Imagine you're trying to find out if y is related to x and figure out the nature
of that relationship. It's rather difficult to parse this information,
especially given that this is just one-fourth of the total. Let's try using some
exploratory statistics to get a better sense of the data: the mean of each
variable, the standard deviation of each variable, the regression line, the
Pearson correlation, and the \(R^2\) value.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;table border="1" class="dataframe"&gt;
  &lt;thead&gt;
    &lt;tr style="text-align: right;"&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(\mu_x\)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(\mu_y\)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(\sigma_x\)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(\sigma_y\)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(r\)&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Regression line&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;\(R^2\)&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;Dataset&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;&lt;/th&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/thead&gt;
  &lt;tbody&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;I&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.501&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.317&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.032&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.816&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.500x + 3.000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.667&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;II&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.501&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.317&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.032&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.816&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.500x + 3.000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.666&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;III&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.500&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.317&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.030&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.816&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.500x + 3.000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.666&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
    &lt;tr&gt;
      &lt;th&gt;IV&lt;/th&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;9.0&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;7.501&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;3.317&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;2.031&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.817&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.500x + 3.000&lt;/td&gt;
      &lt;td&gt;0.667&lt;/td&gt;
    &lt;/tr&gt;
  &lt;/tbody&gt;
&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
The standard statistics we might use when we don't know what we're looking for
yet aren't distinguishing these datasets at all. Let's see what a plot looks
like:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/images/teachback/anscombe.png" alt="nil"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Sometimes a picture really is worth a thousand correlation values:
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The first dataset seems like a fairly standard linear correlation with some
noise: linear regression seems like a good fit.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The second dataset has a very regular relationship, but it's not linear!
Modeling this with a quadratic would work well.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The third dataset has a very regular relationship with one crazy outlier.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The fourth dataset is barely a dataset! Something has gone terribly wrong and
a single influential outlier is preventing us from seeing that in
statistics.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
There is no tool that is more effective at quickly sussing out these patterns
than a visualization like this one.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
That's all for today. Next time I'll talk about visual complexity and visual
overload, and I'll do my part to combat some pernicious misconceptions about how
sophisticated data visualization should be. See you then!
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:34:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Painless Introduction to Python Data Analysis and Visualization</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Data visualization and data science is a hot topic right now, and there's lots of people I know who
want to develop this skill set. A common hurdle, in my experience, is that a lot of tutorials are
either incredibly specific (here's how to change the y-axis title) or very abstract (this is what a
violin plot is, good luck making one!) The goal of this tutorial is to make the kind of resource I
would have really benefited from when I was starting out: an introduction that can give you the
background you need to actually benefit from internal documentation and give you an idea of what's
possible so you aren't reinventing the wheel (an extraordinarily common problem). This post is
written for:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who aren't completely new to computer programming, but not necessarily programmers or software developers
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to know basic Python syntax to follow along, but you don't need to actually know much about Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who is tired of the limitations of programs like Tableau and wants to be able to make
bespoke visualizations that meet their specific needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those who are interested in using Python for statistics or machine learning who want some
wider background before they start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students or presenters of any kind who want to make beautiful graphs without fighting Excel for
an hour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If any of these describe you, you've come to the right place!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (44 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 19:07:24 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>