<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho (Posts about stats)</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/categories/cat_stats.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 22 Apr 2020 04:08:07 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A Whirlwind Tour of Statistical Tests</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Hello again! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's say you've been working on your dataviz skills, and you think you've found an interesting
pattern or correlation in a dataset. How can you tell that whatever you're seeing is significant?
How can you distinguish between random variation and legitimate, meaningful results? As it happens,
the mathematical branch of statistics is almost entirely devoted to questions like these. I think
aspiring data scientists need not be full-fledged statisticians, but everyone should be familiar
with the basic statistical tests, when to apply them, and how to interpret their results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we'll be sojourning through the land of statistical tests in Python, showing how they might be
used and interpreted. The goal is not that you'll be able to apply this all immediately when you
need it; instead, the goal is that you can recognize when statistical tests might be useful and be
able to find the ones you need. (In an age of the Internet, I find recognition to be much more
important than memorizing everything: if you know what to Google, you can figure out how to code it,
but you can't Google something you can't put into words or something you can't recognize.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (20 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>guide</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 17:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>