<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho (Posts about guide)</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/categories/guide.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2021 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Sat, 20 Feb 2021 01:40:58 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Effective Data Visualization, Part 1: What Is Effective Data Visualization?</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;i&gt;This series is the textual version of a presentation I gave to a class on
effective&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;data visualization. I'm reproducing it here both to add some
information that&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;was cut from the presentation for time and to put it in a
publicly available&lt;/i&gt; &lt;i&gt;place.&lt;/i&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div id="outline-container-org286fd4f" class="outline-2"&gt;
&lt;h2 id="org286fd4f"&gt;Intro&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-2" id="text-org286fd4f"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org8e64dca" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org8e64dca"&gt;What This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org8e64dca"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This series of posts is about how to make effective data visualization: exactly
what I mean by that will become clear shortly. Much like one might critique
writing in a creative writing class, I'll focus on how to improve existing
visualizations. This should hopefully also help the reader become a better
consumer of data visualization they encounter in their daily lives.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div id="outline-container-org0a68252" class="outline-3"&gt;
&lt;h3 id="org0a68252"&gt;Who This Guide Is For&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;div class="outline-text-3" id="text-org0a68252"&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
This guide is for anyone! Unlike my other work on this blog, this guide expects
no knowledge of coding or any platform for visualizations: learning such a tool
is necessary to implement these ideas, but not necessary for this guide at all.
My hope is that this is generally useful for people in business, data science,
journalism, programming, and statistics: anyone who works with or cares about
data.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Without further ado, let's get started!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (4 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/effective-data-visualization-part-1-what-is-effective-data-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 19 Feb 2021 19:34:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Whirlwind Tour of Statistical Tests</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Hello again! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's say you've been working on your dataviz skills, and you think you've found an interesting
pattern or correlation in a dataset. How can you tell that whatever you're seeing is significant?
How can you distinguish between random variation and legitimate, meaningful results? As it happens,
the mathematical branch of statistics is almost entirely devoted to questions like these. I think
aspiring data scientists need not be full-fledged statisticians, but everyone should be familiar
with the basic statistical tests, when to apply them, and how to interpret their results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we'll be sojourning through the land of statistical tests in Python, showing how they might be
used and interpreted. The goal is not that you'll be able to apply this all immediately when you
need it; instead, the goal is that you can recognize when statistical tests might be useful and be
able to find the ones you need. (In an age of the Internet, I find recognition to be much more
important than memorizing everything: if you know what to Google, you can figure out how to code it,
but you can't Google something you can't put into words or something you can't recognize.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (20 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>guide</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 17:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Painless Introduction to Python Data Analysis and Visualization</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Data visualization and data science is a hot topic right now, and there's lots of people I know who
want to develop this skill set. A common hurdle, in my experience, is that a lot of tutorials are
either incredibly specific (here's how to change the y-axis title) or very abstract (this is what a
violin plot is, good luck making one!) The goal of this tutorial is to make the kind of resource I
would have really benefited from when I was starting out: an introduction that can give you the
background you need to actually benefit from internal documentation and give you an idea of what's
possible so you aren't reinventing the wheel (an extraordinarily common problem). This post is
written for:
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;People who aren't completely new to computer programming, but not necessarily programmers or software developers
&lt;ul class="org-ul"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;You need to know basic Python syntax to follow along, but you don't need to actually know much about Python&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Anyone who is tired of the limitations of programs like Tableau and wants to be able to make
bespoke visualizations that meet their specific needs&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Those who are interested in using Python for statistics or machine learning who want some
wider background before they start&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Students or presenters of any kind who want to make beautiful graphs without fighting Excel for
an hour&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
If any of these describe you, you've come to the right place!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (44 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>guide</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-painless-introduction-to-python-data-analysis-and-visualization/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 29 Oct 2019 19:07:24 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>