<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>Pollard's Rho (Posts about math)</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/categories/math.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2020 &lt;a href="mailto:nicholas.miklaucic@gmail.com"&gt;Nicholas Miklaucic&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 18:32:20 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>The Basics of Cryptography, Part 1: Diffie-Hellman Key Exchange</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
How can we send secure messages through insecure channels?
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
A quick note before we begin: this summarizes a talk I gave at my high school's computer science
club. It's written to be accessible to anyone with a basic math background, though, and it doesn't
require any programming knowledge. This is the start of a series that will try to explain the basics
of cryptography: given that all of us use cryptography every day, it's important to have a basic
understanding of how it works. It's also pretty cool!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/the-basics-of-cryptography-part-1-diffie-hellman-key-exchange/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 14 Jan 2020 16:09:56 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem-Solving Techniques: Invariants</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
There are a lot of clever proofs in mathematics and computer science. I've already talked about some
of them, and I hope to do a lot more of it on this blog. There's often a certain separation that I
feel when I read something particularly creative or beautiful: this is amazing, but how could I ever
hope to produce something like it? Is real aesthetic achievement in these fields limited to those
with a natural talent I lack? 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
I'm still not sure about that last question, but I do know that, like anything, it is possible to
improve at creative problem-solving through practice. The people I've known who have been best at
doing creative math—the kind that makes perfect sense when you see it but seems impossible to find
if you don't already know it—have built up vast toolboxes of concepts and ideas that are useful in
many different ways across mathematics and computer science. These aren't solutions for a single
problem: they're meta-solutions that serve as an archetype for solutions to a diverse array of
problems. In my experience, the size of that toolbox is what, more than anything else, determines
how effectively one can find creative, novel ways of approaching problems. I'll be talking about one
such tool today: invariants.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (14 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>cs</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/problem-solving-techniques-invariants/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Jan 2020 17:26:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Whirlwind Tour of Statistical Tests</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
Hello again! 
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Let's say you've been working on your dataviz skills, and you think you've found an interesting
pattern or correlation in a dataset. How can you tell that whatever you're seeing is significant?
How can you distinguish between random variation and legitimate, meaningful results? As it happens,
the mathematical branch of statistics is almost entirely devoted to questions like these. I think
aspiring data scientists need not be full-fledged statisticians, but everyone should be familiar
with the basic statistical tests, when to apply them, and how to interpret their results.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
Today we'll be sojourning through the land of statistical tests in Python, showing how they might be
used and interpreted. The goal is not that you'll be able to apply this all immediately when you
need it; instead, the goal is that you can recognize when statistical tests might be useful and be
able to find the ones you need. (In an age of the Internet, I find recognition to be much more
important than memorizing everything: if you know what to Google, you can figure out how to code it,
but you can't Google something you can't put into words or something you can't recognize.)
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (20 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>guide</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/a-whirlwind-tour-of-statistical-tests/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Nov 2019 17:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bayesian Fallacies, Part 2: The Math of the PSAT Math Section</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In the last episode, we introduced two thinking errors that often come up in statistics: Bayes'
paradox and regression to the mean. I proposed that these errors are really two different
manifestations of the same underlying phenomenon, but I haven't done much to actually explain
why. This post will lay the mathematical groundwork for that explanation!
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (12 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-2-the-math-of-the-psat-math-section/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 28 Oct 2019 00:18:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bayesian Fallacies, Part 1: Of Test Scores, Ski Jumps, and Diseases</title><link>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/</link><dc:creator>Nicholas Miklaucic</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
In my intro psych class, we discussed two distinct &lt;i&gt;fallacies&lt;/i&gt;: common systematic errors in how humans
think. These are called &lt;i&gt;Bayes' Paradox&lt;/i&gt; and &lt;i&gt;regression to the mean&lt;/i&gt;. I will claim that both of these
are really manifestations of the same underlying issue, and in actuality are mathematically the
same.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;
This is going to be pretty involved and pretty long, so I'll be splitting it up into parts. The
first part will just cover the basics of what these two fallacies are and provide a mathematical
framework. After that I'll be using computers to analyze the two, and then I'll make the math behind
what we're doing more rigorous.
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/"&gt;Read more…&lt;/a&gt; (13 min remaining to read)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>dataviz</category><category>math</category><guid>https://nicholas-miklaucic.github.io/posts/bayesian-fallacies-part-1-of-test-scores-ski-jumps-and-diseases/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 23 Oct 2019 18:17:52 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>